Conrad mss. 1886-1935 LMC 2434
Lilly Library
Conrad mss.
1886-1983
Lilly Library
Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924.
LMC 2434
8.75 linear feet At least 7 boxes; 45 items
The Conrad mss., 1886-1983, consists of the papers of novelist Joseph Conrad, 1857-1924.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Józef Teodor Conrad Korzeniowski was born in the city of Berdyczów, Ukraine and raised by parents of Polish descent. As a young man he joined first the French Merchant Marine, then an English mercantile ship, and spent fifteen years traveling as a seaman to Africa and other part of the world. He became a British citizen while at sea, changing his name to Joseph Conrad; and when he returned he moved to England and lived the rest of his life there. Conrad wrote the most significant of his novels in the English language, including Lord Jim (1900), Heart of Darkness (1902), Nostromo (1904), The Secret Agent (1907), and Chance (1914).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Clippings; III. Gontran Goulden; IV. Writings.
Scope and Content Note
Major correspondents from the Correspondence series in this collection can be found in the indexing terms.
The Gontran Goulden series contains materials from Goulden's archive detailing his personal and professional relationship with Conrad, including items detailing his dramatic adaptation of The Secret Agent in 1921.
Also included in the collection are notes for speeches given by Conrad in the United States, notes on his books, the short story "Because of the Dollars," a late draft of "Part III" of Suspense, a review of John Galsworthy's The Man of Property, Conrad's 1912 article "Some Aspects of the Admirable Inquiry into the Loss of the Titanic," William McFee's "The Ideal Wife of a Genius," Ford Madox Ford's introduction to The Sisters, two pen and ink sketches, Sir David Low's crayon caricature of Conrad, and photographs.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1986; 1987; 1997; 2009; 2015
Art; Publishers and publishing; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924.; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924--Correspondence.; Clifford, Hugh Charles, Sir, 1866-1941.; Conrad, Jessie; Curle, Richard, 1883-1968.; Garnett, Edward, 1868-1937.; Lee, Vernon, 1856-1935.; Squire, John Collings, Sir, 1884-1958.; Colvin, Sidney, 1845-1927; Unwin, T. Fisher (Thomas Fisher), 1848-1935; Shanks, Edward, 1892-1953; Norman, Henry, 1858-1939; Melrose, Andrew, 1860-1928; Harrison, Austin, 1873-1928; Goldring, Douglas, 1887-1960; Ford, Lionel, 1865-1932; Epstein, Jacob, 1880-1959; Dark, Sidney, 1874-1947; Björkman, Edwin August, 1866-1951.; D'Avray, Charles, 1878-1960; Graves, Charles L. (Charles Larcom), 1856-1944; Lucas, E. V. (Edward Verrall), 1868-1938; Pawling, Sydney S., 1862-1922; Bartimeus
- I. Correspondence.
  General
  Some folders may include writings, photographs, and other accompanying materials.
  - Conrad, Joseph to Klisczewski, Spiridion, 1886, Jan. 6 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, J[oseph] to Mansfield, G[eorge], [1892], Mar. 31 (Box 1)
  - Redmayne, E.B. to Conrad, Joseph, 1895, Apr. 28 (Box 1)
  - Ford, Lionel to Conrad, Joseph, 1895, May 4 (Box 1)
  - Norman, Sir Henry to Conrad, Joseph, 1895, May 16 (Box 1)
  - Redmayne, E.B. to Conrad, Joseph, 1895, May 19 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph, [ca. 1895]; [Two pen and ink sketches] (Box 1)
  - Wall, Nita B. to Conrad, Joseph, 1896, Mar. 21 (Box 1)
  - Graves, C.L. to Conrad, Joseph, [18]96, Jun. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Unwin, T.F., 1897, Jun. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Unwin, T.F., 1897, Nov. 26 (Box 1)
  - Pawling, Sydney Southgate to Conrad, Joseph, 1903, Jan. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Dear Sir., 1903, Jan. 28 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Jo[sep]h to Lucas, [Edward Verrall], 1904, Dec. 1 (Box 1)
  - Rothenstein, Sir William to Conrad, Joseph, 1906, Nov. 1 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, J[oseph] to Colvin, [Sir Sidney], 1908, Dec. 28 (Box 1)
  - Paget, Violet to Conrad, Joseph, 1909, Nov. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Goldring, Douglas, 1910, Dec. 6 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Harrison, [Austin], 1911, Jun. 7 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Davray, Henry Durand, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Bjorkman, E.A. to Conrad, Joseph, 1912, Jun. 11 (Box 1)
  - Rosciszewski, J. de J. to Conrad, Joseph, 1912, Nov. 21 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1912, Nov. 23] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1912, Dec.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1913, Mar. 31] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1913, Jul.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1913, Jul. 13] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1913, Jul. 15] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1913, Aug. 26] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Davray, Henry Durand, 1913, Dec. 13 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914, Feb.]; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914, Mar. 30] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914] Mar. 31.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914, Apr.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard. Cover., [1914, Apr.?] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1914, May 21 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914, Jun. 4] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1914, Jun.] (Box 1)
  - [1914, Jul.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1914, Jul. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1915, Feb. 24] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1915] Mar. 5 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1915, Apr. 20 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1915, May 26 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1915, May] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1915, Jul. 15 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1915, Sept. 22] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1915, Oct. 7 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1916, Feb. 12] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1916, Mar. 4] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1916, Mar. 29 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1916, Apr. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1916, Apr. 16 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1916, Apr.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1916, May 21] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1916, Aug. 20 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, J[ohn] to Conrad, Joseph, 1916, Sept. 25 (Box 1)
  - Martin, James to Conrad, Joseph, 1916, Sept. 30 (Box 1)
  - Twentyman, E.W.G. to Conrad, Joseph, [19]16, Oct. 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, J[oseph] to Melrose, [Andrew], [1916] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1917, Mar. 27 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1917, Dec. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, J[oseph] to Colvin, [Sir Sidney], 1918, Jun. 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1918, Oct. 9 (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Sir Hugh to Conrad, Joseph, 1918, Nov. 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Conrad, Mrs. Jessie (George), [1919, Feb.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph. Rescue., 1919, Mar. 24 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard., 1919, May 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1919, Jun. 19] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1919, Jun. 28] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Jul. 7 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Jul. 8 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Jul. 16 (Box 1)
  - Robinson, Alex to Conrad, Joseph, 1919, Jul. 29 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Aug. 4 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Aug. 24 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Aug. 30 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Oct. 15 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard 1919, Nov. 11. Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Nov. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Nov. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1919, Nov. 26] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Dec. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1919, Dec. 31 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Jan. 19 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Jan. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Feb. 11 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Feb. 26 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Mar. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Mar. 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Mar. 23 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Apr. 8 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, May 5 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, May 15 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, May 24 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Jun. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Jun. 14 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1920, Jun. 22] (Box 1)
  - Dark, Sidney to Conrad, Joseph, 1920, Jul. 6 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Aug. 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Oct. 9 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1920, Nov. 22 (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Sir Hugh to Conrad, Joseph, 1921, Jan. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Jan. 22 (Box 1)
  - Dent, H.R. to Conrad, Joseph, 1921, Apr. 16 (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Sir Hugh to Conrad, Joseph, 1921, May 31 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Jun. 9 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Galsworthy, John, 1921, Jun. 16 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Jul. 27 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Aug. 1 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Aug. 31 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Sept. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard. Cover., 1921, Sept. 27 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Oct. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Oct. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1921, Nov. 5] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Nov. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1921, Nov. 18] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Nov. 23 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1921, Dec. 16 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Feb.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Mar. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Mar. 20] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Mar. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Apr. 5] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Apr. 24 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Apr. 29] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, May 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, May 10 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, May 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Jun. 29 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Jul. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard. Cover., 1922, Jul. 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Jul. 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Aug. 23 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Oct. 1 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Oct. 16] (Box 1)
  - or Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Oct.; Nov.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Nov. 14 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Nov. 20 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Nov. 21] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, J[oseph] to Squire, [Sir John Collings], 1922, Nov. 30 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Dec. 5] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Dec. 8 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1922, Dec. 15] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1922, Dec. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jan. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jan. 6 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1923, Feb. 2] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Mar. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Mar. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Apr. 10 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Apr. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, May 11 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, May 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jun. 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jul. 14 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jul. 17 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jul. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Jul. 30 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Aug. 28 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Sept. 1 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Sept. 7 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Sept. 20 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1923, Sept.?] (Box 1)
  - Low, [David]. Joseph Conrad: [a crayon caricature], 1923, Sept. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Oct. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Oct. 5 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Mansfield, G[eorge], 1923, Oct. 19 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Oct. 25 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Oct. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1923, Oct.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Nov. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Nov. 5 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Nov. 12 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1923, Nov.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1923, Nov.] (Box 1)
  - Niven, J.C. to Conrad, Joseph, 1923, Dec. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Dec. 17 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1923, Dec. 27 (Box 1)
  - Ritchie, L.A. da C. to Conrad, Joseph, 1923, Dec. 29 (Box 1)
  - C[onrad], J[oseph] [Notes for speeches in America], 1923 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Jan. 14 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924, Jan.] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Feb. 1 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Mar. 4 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Mrs. Jessie (George) to Curle, Richard, 1924, Mar. 10 (Box 1)
  - Shanks, Edward to Conrad, Joseph., [19]24, Mar. 18 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Mar. 25 (Box 1)
  - Epstein, Sir Jacob to Conrad, Joseph, 1924, Apr. 3 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924, May 1] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924, May] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924, Jun. 10] (Box 1)
  - Clifford, Sir Hugh to Conrad, Joseph, 1924, Jun. 15 (Box 1)
  - Joseph Conrad in his garden at Oswalds, Bishopsbourne, 1924, Jun. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924], Jul. 2 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, [1924], Jul. 8 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Jul. 22 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, 1924, Jul. 31 (Box 1)
  - McFee, William. Introduction to Almayer's Folly., [c. 1925] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Mrs. Jessie (George) to Partington, W.G., 1927, Aug. 1 (Box 1)
  - McFee, William. Ecola, [1928] (Box 1)
  - McFee, William. A Most Pirated Maiden, [1928] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Mrs. Jessie (George) to Thorne, Mrs., 1929, May 2 (Box 1)
  - McFee, William. The Ideal Wife of a Genius, [1935] (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Mrs. Jessie (George). Preface to Joseph Conrad's Letters to His Wife, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Brooke, Margaret, ranee of Sarawak to Conrad, Joseph, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph. Second note [conclusion to The Arrow of Gold], Undated. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph. [Suspense: late draft of Part III....], Undated. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph. [Suspense: fragments of a working draft], Undated. (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Joseph to Curle, Richard, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Photographs and newspaper and magazine pictures, Undated. (Box 1)
- II. Clippings.
  - 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974, Jan.-Nov. (Box 1)
  - 1974, Dec (Box 1)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- III. Gontran Goulden.
  - Correspondence, from Joseph Conrad and others., 1921-1983 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Joseph Conrad (Box 1)
  - Printed (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence concerning quotations... (for The Secret Agent) photocopy (Box 1)
  - The Secret Agent title-page mock-up (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- IV. Writings.
  - Introduction to The Sisters. Typescript with author's corrections., 1928 (Bound 1)
  - Because of the Dollars. Revised typewritten manuscript., Undated (Bound 2)
  - Notes on My Books. Dummy manuscript., Undated (Bound 3)
  - Letters of Joseph Conrad to Richard Curle. Typescript and proof sheets with corrections., Undated (Bound 4)
  - The Richard Curle Collection of Conrad., Undated (Bound 5)
  - Some Aspects of the English Titanic Inquiry. Author's manuscript. The English Review, Jul. 1912 (Bound 6)
- Additions
  - Correspondence
    - Conrad, John to Ugo Mursia, 25 May 1974 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Discusses John Conrad's recollections of his father's early life
    - Holbrook, Jackson, 20 March 1915 (Box 2)
      Augotraph letter signed from Conrad to Jackson Holbrook thanking him for his article on Conrad
    - Holland, Michael, 4 December 1909-29 December 1923 (Box 2)
      Ten autograph letters signed from Conrad to Michael James Holland
    - Holt, Lawrence Durning and G. Jean-Aubry, 20 July 1920-1 August 1920 (Box 2)
      Includes four letters, three autograph and one typed, by Conrad to Holt of the Ocean Steam Ship Company about establishing a training sailing ship for the merchant service and the resulting "Memorandum" (see "Memorandum" in Writings series). Also includes two letters, one autograph and one typed, by G. Jean-Aubry to Holt about Conrad's "Memorandum"
    - Newbolt, Henry and William Rothenstein, 4 June 1904-10 April 1906; (2 folders) (Box 2)
      Includes 10 autograph letters signed from Conrad to Newbolt concerning the grant to Conrad of 500 pounds from the Royal Bounty Fund. Also includes 24 autograph letters and cards from Rothenstein to Newbolt regarding financial assistance for Conrad, as well as 1 letter from Alice Rothenstein to Newbolt, 7 from Edmund Gosse to Newbolt on his work on Conrad's behalf, 2 draft letters from Newbolt to Conrad, a letter from the Prime Minister's office confirming the grant to Conrad, and a bank account book in the names of Newbolt and Rothenstein recording the payment in instlaments of the grant to Conrad along with 22 cheques and 2 books of cheque stubs
    - Sandeman, Christopher, 28 August 1916-21 November 1922 (Box 2)
      Twenty-three letters signed from Conrad to Christopher Sandeman about the progress of World War One and related international affairs
    - Sanderson, Ted and Helen Watson, 14 August 1895-14 November 1896 (Box 2)
      Six autograph letters from Conrad to Ted Sanderson and his fiancee Helen Watson about Sanderson and Watson's relationship. Also includes three letters from Sanderson to Watson and four letters from Watson to Sanderson
    - Unknown, 23 February 1922 (Box 2)
      Autograph letter signed to unknown recipient responding to a letter of appreciation
  - Writings
    - "Memorandum: on the scheme for fitting out a sailing-ship for the purpose of perfecting the training of Merchant Service Officers belonging to the Port of Liverpool", 24-25 July 1920 (Box 2)
      Corrected signed typescript
    - "Polish Question: Note on the joint Protectorate of the Western Powers and Russia", 1916 (Box 2)
      Corrected typescript
    - "The End of the Tether", 1902 (Box 2)
      Autograph manuscript leaf with autograph revisions
    - "To the Editor of Daily Express", 10 June 1914 (Bound 7)
      Autograph manuscript with corrections